Guide to the Samuel L. Clemens Papers, 1796-1984 (bulk 1853-1909)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Samuel L. Clemens Papers
1796-1984
1853-1909
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910
12 cubic feet (37 boxes, 5 framed items)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Includes manuscripts, notes, diaries, clippings, certificates, deeds and photographs; but of particular note are the letters Clemens wrote to his family describing his early adulthood as well as the development and progression of his writing career.
Biographical Note
Samuel Langhorne Clemens was born November 30, 1835 in Florida, Missouri, and died April 21, 1910 in Redding, Connecticut. He married Olivia Langdon in 1870 and they had four children: Langdon, Olivia Susan ("Suzy"), Clara, and Jane ("Jean"). Additional biographical information is readily available; however, some further genealogical information is helpful in explaining the inclusion of the Clemens material in the McKinney Family Papers:
Clemens' parents were John Marshall Clemens and Jane Lampton Clemens. Their children were Samuel, Orion (1825-1897), Pamela (1827-1904), Pleasant (1828-1829), Margaret (1830-1839), Benjamin (1832-1842) and Henry (1838-1858). SLC's sister Pamela married William Anderson Moffett, and they had a daughter Annie. Annie Moffet married Charles Webster, and one of their children was Alice Jane Webster. While at boarding school, Alice Jane changed her name to Jean and continued to use the name Jean Webster for the rest of her professional life. However, after marrying Glenn Ford McKinney, she was also known as Jean Webster McKinney.
Scope and Content Note
Papers of Samuel L. Clemens include manuscripts of his stories written or signed by Clemens and one notebook, 1855-1868; his letters and telegrams to family members Orion Clemens, Pamela C. Moffett, Charles L. Webster, Jane L. Clemens, and others, 1853-1909, concerning his early experiences in Philadelphia, travelling, business affairs, mining in the American West, his writing and publishing affairs, trips to Hawaii in 1866 and Europe in 1867, political figures, his typesetting business, and family affairs; letters received, including several from William Dean Howells, 1874-1909, and later letters about Mark Twain history and materials, 1941-1975; and letters to Charles L. Webster from Clemens and illustrator E.W. Kemble about his illustrations for Huckleberry Finn and original and proof copies of Kemble's illustrations, 1884.
Other items include original manuscript memoirs on the Civil War by Gen. U.S. Grant, letters to Charles L. Webster from Grant, his photographs of Grant, Civil War scenes, and Grant's funeral, 1863-1885; manuscripts, diary entries, letters, clippings, and photographs of Isabel Van Kleek Lyon, Clemens' secretary, concerning the person and career of Samuel L. Clemens, 1903-1939, and notes from a conversation with Lyon by Samuel and Doris Webster, 1950-1953; letters, clippings, memoranda, legal papers, certificates, deeds, and contracts of Samuel L. Clemens' family members, 1807 and 1834-1944, including his parents John Marshall and Jane Lampton Clemens, his brothers Orion Clemens, Henry Clemens, his daughters Clara and Jean, and his sister Pamela Clemens Moffett, her husband William Anderson Moffett, their son Samuel E. Moffett, and their daughter Annie Moffett and her husband Charles L. Webster; and photographs of Samuel L. Clemens, his family, and related Websters, Moffetts, Fords, Dalrimples, and McKinneys, circa 1856-1955.
The Samuel L. Clemens Papers form part of the McKinney Family Papers.
Access
Researchers will be asked to use photocopies of most correspondence in the collection unless there is a specific need for the originals. Otherwise, this collection is open for research according to the regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library without any additional restrictions.
Related Materials
McKinney Family Papers
Jean Webster Papers
Margery Clinton Papers
Autograph Files
Subject Headings
Names:
Webster, Doris; Webster, Samuel; McKinney, Jean Webster, 1876-1916
Twain, Mark, 1835-1910; Clemens, Orion, 1825-1897; Webster, Charles L., 1851-1891; Howells, William Dean, 1837-1920; Kemble, E. W. (Edward Windsor) 1861-1933; Grant, Ulysses S. (Ulysses Simpson), 1822-1885; Lyon, Isabel, 1863-1958; Clemens, John Marshall, 1798-1847; Clemens, Jane Lampton, 1803-1890; Clemens, Henry, 1838-1858; Clemens, Clara; Clemens, Jean, 1880-1909; Moffett, Pamela Clemens, 1827-1904; Moffett, William Anderson; Moffett, Samuel E.; Webster, Annie Moffett; Clemens, Samuel Langhorne, 1835-1910; Moffett, Annie; Clemens family; Moffett family; Webster family; Ford family; Dalrymple family; McKinney family
Subjects:
Family--New York (State); Real property; American literature; Publishers and publishing; Authors, American--20th century--Correspondence; Humorists, American--20th century--Correspondence; Mines and mineral resources--West (U.S.); Illustrated books, Children's; Funeral service; Women--Diaries; Type-setting
Places:
United States--Politics and government--19th century; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; Hawaii--Description and travel; Philadelphia (Pa.)--Description; Europe--Description and travel
Document Types:
Photographs; Autographs; Correspondence
VCL Categories:
Family; Literature and Writing
Note
Forms part of the McKinney Family Papers.
Encoding Information
Encoded by Elizabeth Clarke, June 2007. Updated by Emma Gronbeck, May 2023.
Acquisition Information
Included in the gift of the Jean Webster McKenney Family Papers, given to the college in 1977 by Jean Connor, Jean Webster's daughter, and her husband, Ralph Connor. Additional materials were purchased from a variety of sources in subsequent years.
Other Formats
The bulk of the collection is available on microfilm.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The microfilm copy of the collection requires a microfilm reader.
Series List
- Series A. Samuel L. Clemens Manuscripts, (Box 1)
- Series B. Samuel L. Clemens Correspondence To Family Members, (Boxes 2-10)
- Series C. Correspondence To Samuel L. Clemens and Related Letters, (Boxes 10-11)
- Series D. Olivia Langdon Clemens Correspondence to Family Members, (Box 12)
- Series E. Clara Clemens Correspondence To Family, (Box 12)
- Series F. Jean L. Clemens Correspondence to Family, (Box 12)
- Series G. Susan Clemens, (Box 12)
- Series H. Mark Twain Birthday Celebrations, (Box 12)
- Series I. Samuel Langhorne Clemens' Funeral, (Box 12)
- Series J. Mark Twain's Homes, (Box 12)
- Series K. Mark Twain Clippings, (Boxes 13 and 37)
- Series L. Mississippi Life, (Box 14)
- Series M. Copies of Mark Twain Publications, (Box 14)
- Series N. The Mentor Magazine, (Box 14)
- Series O. Mark Twain Society's Publications, (Box 14)
- Series P. Materials Related to Huckleberry Finn, (Boxes 15-16 and 36)
- Series Q. Papers of Isabel Van Kleek Lyon, Secretary to Samuel L. Clemens, (Boxes 17-22)
- Series R. John Marshall Clemens Correspondence, (Box 23)
- Series S. Jane Lampton Clemens Correspondence, (Box 23)
- Series T. Orion Clemens Correspondence, (Box 23)
- Series U. Henry Clemens Correspondence, (Box 23)
- Series V. Pamela Clemens Moffet Correspondence, (Box 24)
- Series W. William Anderson Moffett Correspondence, (Box 24)
- Series X. Moffett-Bryan-Boone Lineage, (Box 24)
- Series Y. Erasmus M. Moffett Correspondence, (Box 24)
- Series Z. Samuel E. Moffett Correspondence, (Box 24)
- Series AA. Annie Moffett Webster Correspondence, (Boxes 24-25 and 35)
- Series BB. Walter Janes' Published Works, (Box 26)
- Series CC. Calvin Whitney Correspondence, (Box 26)
- Series DD. Luther Webster and Maria Whitney Webster, His Wife, Correspondence, (Box 26)
- Series EE. Charles L. Webster Correspondence Sent, (Box 27)
- Series FF. Charles L. Webster – Samuel L. Clemens Contracts, (Box 27)
- Series GG. Charles L. Webster Notebooks, (Box 28)
- Series HH. Charles L. Webster Correspondence Received, (Boxes 29-31)
- Series JJ. Charles L. Webster Correspondence Concerning General U.S. Grant's Memoirs, (Boxes 31-32)
- Series KK. "Personal Memoirs" of General U.S. Grant Manuscript, (Box 32)
- Series LL. Sir Charles L. Webster, Knight of the Order of Piano (Pius), Vatican, Rome Correspondence, (Box 33)
- Series MM. Estate of Charles L. Webster, (Box 33)
- Series NN. William Luther Webster Correspondence, (Box 33)
- Series OO. Samuel Charles Webster Correspondence, (Box 33)
- Series PP. Photographs (not microfilmed), (Boxes 33 and 37)
- Series QQ. Ephemera (not microfilmed), (Box 36)
- Series RR. Framed Portraits, (Framed Storage)
Container List
The folder numbers that are listed below, represent the current location of the materials and those in brackets represent the old paper guide and microfilm organization. Please use the current folder numbers.
- Series A. Samuel L. Clemens Manuscripts
  - "Jul'us Caesar,", 1853 (1.1 [A.1])
  - Notebook, bound, Samuel Clemens, 1855 (1.2 [A.2])
  - "Assaying in Nevada by Mark Twain,", 1863 (1.3 [A.3])
  - Remarkable Sagacity of a Cat, 1863 (1.4 [A.4])
  - Sarezzy, 1864 (1.5 [A.5])
  - Jumping Frog, 1865 (1.6 [A.6])
  - Colonel Foster, 1867 (1.7 [A.7])
  - "Vail's courtship,", [1867]; (fragment [not microfilmed]) (Box 36)
  - Ghost Life on the Mississippi, 1871 (1.8 [A.8])
  - Smithsonian Institute for the Diffusion of Knowledge, undated (1.9 [A.9])
  - Riot, Oct 1865 (1.10 [A10])
  - On Rational Religion, undated (1.11 [A.11])
  - A Plea for Old Jokes, undated (1.12 [A.12])
  - Incomplete Sketches, Mark Twain, undated (1.13 [A.13])
  - Who Made the Grass?, undated (1.14 [A.14])
  - I Rise to a Question of Privilege, undated (1.15 [A.15])
  - Kingdom of Wittenburg, undated (1.16 [A.16])
  - Interview with Gen. Grant, undated (1.17 [A.17])
  - Taming the Bicycle, undated (1.18 [A.18a])
  - Taming the Bicycle, undated (1.19 [A.18b])
  - On Opera, undated (1.20 [A.19])
  - Innocents, Abroad, reject sheets pp. 1-27, undated (1.21 [A.20])
  - Innocents, Abroad, pp. 3-12, undated (1.22 [A.21])
  - Innocents, Abroad, pp. 50-61, undated (1.23 [A.22])
  - Innocents, Abroad, pp. 71-98, undated (1.24 [A.23])
  - Innocents, Abroad, pp. 378-9, 398-9, undated (1.25 [A.24])
  - Devil's Gate, pp. 501-3, undated (1.26 [A.25])
  - Devil's Gate, pp. 959-963 (CRW Note: "part missing), undated (1.27 [A.26])
  - Devil's Gate, pp. 1256-1258, 1289-133, undated (1.28 [A.27])
  - Colonel Sellers (W.D. Howell's Handwriting) The Golden Age – play, 1884 (1.29 [A.28])
- Series B. Samuel L. Clemens Correspondence To Family Members
  - "Dear Brother..." Philadelphia, 26 Oct 1853 (2.1 [B.1 ])
  - "My Dear Brother..." Philadelphia, 28 Nov 1853 (2.2 [B.2 ])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Philadelphia, 5 Dec 1853 (2.2 [B.2A (formerly B.4)])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Keokuk, 5 Aug 1856 (2.3 [B.3 ])
  - "Dear Belle…"Cairo and clipping from Kansas City Star "Letters Mark Twain Wrote in 1857,", 11 Aug 1857 (2.4 [B.5 ])
  - "Dear Brother and Sister…" Saint Louis, 9 Mar 1858 (2.5 [B.6 ])
  - Fragment of letter to Orion, undated (2.6 [B.7 ])
  - "Dear Brother..." New Orleans, 28 Sep 1860 (2.7 [B.8 ])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Steamer "Alonzo Child,", 6 Feb 1861 (2.8 [B.9 ])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Steamer "Hannibal City,", 26 Apr 1861 (2.9 [B.10])
  - Letter to Orion from Edward Bates, Washington, 31 July 1861 (2.9 [B.10A (formerly B.34)])
  - "My Dear Sister…/ My Dear Mother…" Carson City, 25 Oct 1861 (2.10 [B.11])
  - Deed from D.C. Crooker to Samuel L. Clemens, 21 July 1862 (2.11 [B.12])
  - NY Times Clipping - "Money Belt Found in Nevada Inscribed 'Samuel Clemens,'", 1 Apr 1966 (2.12 [B.13])
  - Envelope introducing Mr.DeKay, O. Clemens Esq., Carson City, NT, undated (2.12 [B.14])
  - Sonora Silver Mining Co. Stock Certificate S. Clemens, 1 Aug 1863 (2.13 [B.15])
  - On the Little Square Package…, Feb 1862 (2.13 [B.15A (formerly B.36) ])
  - "My Dear Mother…" Carson City, 8 Feb 1862 (2.14 [B.16])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, 9 Feb 1862 (2.14 [B.17])
  - "Dear Mother…" Carson City, 2 Apr 1862 (2.15 [B.18])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Carson City, 1862 (2.15 [B.19])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 13 Apr 1862 (2.16 [B.20])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Esmeralda, Thursday, 24 Apr 1862 (2.16 [B.20A (formerly B.38)])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, PS Friday Morning, 1862 (2.16 [B.20B])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 28 Apr 1862 (2.17 [B.21])
  - Letter to [Mary E. "Mollie" Clemens], "Well although I believe I never had the pleasure of her acquaintance…", [12? Sep 1861] (2.18 [B.22])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 11-12 May 1862 (2.19 [B.25])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Esmeralda, 12 May 1862 (2.19 [B.26])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 4 May 1862 (2.20 [B.27])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 4 May 1862 (2.21 [B.27A])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 17 May 1862 (2.22 [B.28])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 25 June 1862 (2.23 [B.29])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 2 June 1862 (2.24 [B.30])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 9 June 1862 (2.25 [B.31])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 23 July 1862 (2.26 [B.32])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 30 July 1862 (2.27 [B.33])
  - "My Dear Brother…" Esmeralda, 7 Aug 1862 (2.28 [B.37])
  - Clippings Mark Twain's Golden Dream et al., undated (2.29 [B.39])
  - "To the Hon. The Sec'y amd Deputy Sec N.T…." Virginia City, N.T., 21 Oct 1862 (2.30 [B.40])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Office Daily Territorial Enterprise, 16 Feb 1863 (2.31 [B.41])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, "Bully for Mrs. Hooliday,", undated (2.32 [B.45])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Virginia, 11 Apr 1863 (2.33 [B.46])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, " Eds. Golden Era…", undated (2.34 [B.47])
  - Mississippi River Leadline Chant by Julian Lee Rayford, undated (2.35 [B.48])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Lick House, S.F., 1 June 1863 (2.36 [B.49])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Steamboat Springs, 19 Aug 1863 (2.36 [B.49A] (formerly B.44))
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Virginia, 11 Apr 1863 (2.36 [B.49B (formerly B.42)])
  - Billing Executive Depart. N.T. To Adv. Proclamation $30.000. Cold hill Daily News Dr., 17 Apr 1864 (2.37 [B.50])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" San Francisco, 25 Sep 1864 (2.38 [B.51])
  - Paradise of the Pacific, Clipping Mark Twain's Mantelpiece, Oct 1908 (2.39 [B.53])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" San Francisco, 5 Mar 1866 (2.40 [B.54])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Honolulu Sandwich Islands, 3 Apr 1866 (2.41 [B.55])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Wailuku Sugar Plantation, 4 May 1866 (2.42 [B.56])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Honolulu, 22 May 1866 (2.43 [B.57])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Honolulu Sandwich Islands, 21 June 1866 (2.44 [B.58])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" Honolulu, 27 June 1866 (2.45 [B.59])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" On Board Ship Smyoniate, At Sea, 30 July 1866 (2.46 [B.60])
  - All the Folks, Affectionate Greeting…" Va., 1 Nov 1866 (2.47 [B.61])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, circa 1866 (2.48 [B.62])
  - "Dear Folks…" San Francisco - Midnight, 4 Dec 1866 (2.49 [B.63])
  - "Dear Folks…" San Francisco, 14 Dec 1866 (2.50 [B.64])
  - "Dear Mollie…" New York, Feb 1867 (2.51 [B.65])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, 1867 (2.52 [B.66])
  - Letter engaging SLC as special correspondent on excursion to the Holy Land, Alta California Office 42 John St. New York, 1867 (2.53 [B.67])
  - "Dear Folks…" Westminster Hotel, 1 May 1867 (2.54 [B.68])
  - "Dear Folks…" Westminster Hotel, New York, 1 June 1867 (2.55 [B.69])
  - Intro SLC to L. Bucher and W.D. Spaulding, Office of the Tribune, New York, 5 June 1867 (2.56 [B.70])
  - Unidentified title, Poughkeepsie Journal clipping, 20 Dec 1964 (2.57 [B.71])
  - "Dear Folks…" New York, 7 June 1867 (2.58 [B.72])
  - Envelope containing SLC's notes of items brought home 1867 from Innocents Abroad trip to SS Quaker City (2.59 [B.73])
  - "Dear Folks…" Fayal Azores, 20 June 1867 (2.60 [B.74])
  - Cape Spartel photograph with notes by SLC on back, Feb 1867 (2.61 [B.75])
  - "My Dear Lily…" Grand Hotel Marseille, 12 July 1867 (2.62 [B.76])
  - "Dear Folks…" Genoa, Italy, 14 July 1867 (2.63 [B.77])
  - "Dear Folks…" Yalta, Russia, 25 Aug 1867 (2.64 [B.78])
  - To His Imperial Majesty Alexander III, Emperor of Russia, 1867 (2.65 [B.79])
  - "Dear Folks…" Constantinople, 1 Sep 1867 (2.66 [B.80])
  - "Dear Folks…" U.S. Consul's Office Beirut, Syria, 11 Sep 1867 (2.67 [B.81])
  - "Dear Folks…" Cagliari Sardinia, 12 Oct 1867 (2.68 [B.82])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Cadiz, 24 Oct 1867 (2.69 [B.83])
  - "Dear Folks…" New York, 19 Nov 1867; (original missing, photocopy only available) (2.70 [B.84])
  - "Dear Folks…" New York, 20 Nov 1867 (2.71 [B.85])
  - "Dear Folks…" Washington, 25 Nov 1867 (2.72 [B.86])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, 224 F St., Washington, 10 Dec 1867 (2.73 [B.87])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" 224 F St., Washington, 8 Jan 1868 (3.1 [B.88])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" 224 F St., Washington, 9 Jan 1868 (3.2 [B. 89])
  - "Dear Folks…", 13 Jan 1868 (3.2 [B.89A])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" 224 F St., Washington, 6 Feb 1868 (3.3 [B.90])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Hartford Conn., 24 Jan 1868 (3.4 [B.91])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, 224 F St., Washington, 21 Feb 1868 (3.5 [B.92])
  - "Dear Folks…" At Sea, 15 Mar 1868 (3.6 [B.94])
  - "Dear Folks…" Elmira, NY, 24 Aug 1868 (3.7 [B.95])
  - "Dear Mother…" Everett House, New York Election Day, 1868 (3.8 [B.96])
  - "Dear Folks…" Cleveland, 18 Nov 1868 (3.9 [B.97])
  - "Dear Folks…" Cleveland, 20 Nov 1868 (3.10 [B.98])
  - "Dear Folks…" Everett House, NY, 10 Dec 1868 (3.11 [B.100])
  - "My dear Sister…" Lansing, Michigan, 24 Dec 1868 (3.12 [B.100A (formerly B.107)])
  - "My Dear Sister…" PRIVATE, Davenport, Iowa, 14 Jan 1869 (3.12 [B.101])
  - "My Dear Sister…", 14 Feb 1869 (3.13 [B.102])
  - "Dear Folks…" Lockport, NY, 27 Feb 1869 (3.13 [B.102A (formerly B.93)])
  - "Dear Folks…" Elmira, 4 June 1869 (3.14 [B.103])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Buffalo, 20 Aug 1869 (3.15 [B.104])
  - "P.S. I forgot…" Buffalo, 21 Aug 1869 (3.16 [B.105])
  - "Dear Mrs. Langdon…" Everett House, NY, 1869 (3.17 [B.106])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Utica, NY, Baggs Hotel, 15 Jan 1870 (3.18 [B.108])
  - "Dear Folks…" Buffalo, 26 Mar 1870 (3.19 [B.109])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Buffalo, 1870 (3.20 [B.110])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Buffalo, 12 June 1870 (3.21 [B.111])
  - 3 part of letter to Orion and Mollie Clemens, 1870 (3.22 [B.112])
  - "Dear Brother…" Elmira, 6 [no month] 1870 (3.23 [B.113])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" J. Langdon, Miner and Dealer, Elmira, NY, 25 June 1870 (3.24 [B.114])
  - "Dear Folks…" Elmira, 27 July 1870 (3.25 [B.115])
  - From SLC, "Father died this afternoon,", 6 Aug 1870; (telegram) (3.26 [B.116])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Buffalo, 31 Aug 1870 (3.27 [B.117])
  - "Dear Folks…" Buffalo, 17 [no month] 1870 (3.28 [B.118])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Buffalo, 9 [no month] 1870 (3.29 [B.119])
  - "Dear Clemens…" 149 Asylum Ave., Hartford, 18 Nov 1870 (3.30 [B.120])
  - "Dear Pamela..." Letter from Olivia Clemens, Buffalo, 3 Feb 1871 (3.31 [B.121])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Buffalo, 4 [no month] 1871 (3.32 [B.122])
  - "Dear Folks…" Buffalo, 15 [no month] 1871 (3.33 [B.123])
  - "Dear Bro…" Elmira, 30 [no month] 1871 (3.34 [B.124])
  - "Dear Annie…" Elmira, 17 May 1872 (3.35 [B.125])
  - "Dear Mother and Sister…" London, 6 Nov 1872 (3.36 [B.126])
  - "Dear Folks…" Hartford, 26 Nov 1872 (3.37 [B.127])
  - "Dear Folks…" Hartford, 5 Dec 1872 (3.38 [B.128])
  - "My Dear Folks…"20 Bromfield St., Boston, 15 Dec 1872 (3.39 [B.129])
  - "Dear Ma, Pamela, Annie, and Sammie…" Letter from Livy, Hartford, 20 Dec 1872 (3.40 [B.130])
  - "Dear Ma and Pamela…" London, Edwards Hotel, George St., Hanover sq, 15 June 1873 (3.41 [B.132])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Saturday, 1873 (3.42 [B.133])
  - Letter from Livy to Ma and Pamela, London, July 1873 (3.43 [B.134])
  - Letter from Livy to Ma and Pamela, Edinburgh, 15 Aug 1873 (3.44 [B.135])
  - Letter from SLC to Orion, London, Sep 1873 (3.45 [B.136])
  - "Dear Mollie…" Letter from Livy, Hartford, 11 Jan 1874 (3.46 [B.137])
  - "Dear Mother…" Elmira, 10 May 1874 (3.47 [B.138])
  - "Dear Brother…" Hartford, 9 Dec 1874 (3.48 [B.139])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…", 14 May 1874 (3.49 [B.140])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Thursday, 18 May 1874 (3.49 [B.140A])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Hartford, 23 July 1875 (3.50 [B.141])
  - "My Dear Niece…" Letter to Annie M. Webster, Elmira, 1 Sep 1876 (3.51 [B.142])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Hartford, 9 June 1876 (3.52 [B.143])
  - "My Dear Sister…", 23 July 1876 (3.53 [B.144])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, 22 Dec 1875 (3.54 [B.145])
  - "My dear Sister…" Saturday, 1877 (3.55 [B.146])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Monday, 1877 (3.55 [B.146A])
  - Letter to unidentified correspondent, Hartford, 1877 (3.56 [B.147])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Hartford, 28 Feb 1877 (3.57 [B.148])
  - "Dear Mother…", 7 Apr 1878 (3.58 [B.149])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Paris, 29 May 1879 (3.59 [B.150])
  - "Dear Pamela..." Elmira, 15 Sep 1879 (3.60 [B.151])
  - "Dear Bro…" Home, 17 Nov 1879 (3.61 [B.152])
  - "My dear Sister…", 20 Dec 1879 (3.62 [B.153])
  - Mrs. P.A. Moffett, Fredonia, NY, 1879 (3.63 [B.154])
  - Remington Typewriter Co. adv. Quoting MT's Ltrs of 19 Mar 1875 and Jan 1904, 1879 (3.64 [B.155])
  - Letter to Pamela, 1880; (missing pp.3-8) (3.65 [B.156])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Hartford, 4 Feb 1880 (3.66 [B.157])
  - "My Dear Mother…" Hartford, 17 Feb 1880 (3.67 [B.158])
  - "My Dear Mother…", 7 Jan 1880 (3.68 [B.159])
  - "My dear Sister…", 25 Jan 1880 (3.69 [B.160])
  - "My Dear Bro…", 26 Feb 1880 (3.70 [B.161])
  - "Dear Bro…", 5 Mar 1880 (3.71 [B.162])
  - "My Dear Bro…", 4 Apr 1880 (3.72 [B.163])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Sunday, 1880 (3.73 [B.164])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Wednesday, 1880 (3.74 [B.165])
  - Elmira, NY - J. Langdon and Co., 29 June 1880 (3.75 [B.166])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Hartford, 27 Nov 1880 (3.76 [B.167])
  - "Dear Dan…" Hartford, 16 Dec 1880 (3.77 [B.168])
  - "My Dear Bro…" Hartford, 17 Dec 1880 (3.78 [B.169])
  - Letters Patent No. 5170 1878. Assignment to Daniel Slote of NYC, 1881 (4.1 [B.170])
  - "Dear Dan…", 26 Jan 1881 (4.2 [B.171])
  - "Dear Mother…" Hartford, Feb 1881 (4.3 [B.172])
  - "Dear Dan…" Boston, 24 Feb 1881 (4.4 [B.173])
  - "Dear Dan…" Saturday, 1881 (4.5 [B.174])
  - "Dear Dan…", 1881 (4.6 [B.175])
  - "My Dear Sister…" Hartford, 16 Mar 1881 (4.7 [B.176])
  - "Dear Dan…", 1881 (4.8 [B.177])
  - "Mr. [Charles] L. Webster…" Hartford, 29 Apr 1881 (4.9 [B.178])
  - "Dear Charley…", 1 May 1881 (4.10 [B.179])
  - "Dear Charley…" Hartford, 1 May 1881 (4.11 [B.180])
  - "Dear Charley…", 2 May 1881 (4.12 [B.181])
  - "My Dear Mother and Sister…" Hartford, 2 May 1881 (4.13 [B.182])
  - "Dear Charley…", 3 May 1881 (4.14 [B.183])
  - "Dear Charley…", 1881 (4.15 [B.184])
  - "Dear Charley…", 6 May 1881 (4.16 [B.185])
  - To Charlie - "I have Hubbard's newspaper…", 1881 (4.17 [B.186])
  - "Dear Charley…" Hartford, 7 May 1881 (4.18 [B.187])
  - "Dear Charley…" Hartford, 14 May 1881 (4.19 [B.188])
  - "Dear Charley…" Hartford, 16 May 1881 (4.20 [B.189])
  - "Dear Charley…" Hartford, 19 May 1881 (4.21 [B.190])
  - "Dear Charley…" Tuesday, 1881 (4.22 [B.191])
  - Charley, See Frank and…, 1881 (4.23 [B.192])
  - Telegram to CL Webster K. Engraving Co., Hartford, 20 May 1881 (4.24 [B.193])
  - "Dear Sir…" Hartford, Wednesday, 1881 (4.25 [B.194])
  - "Dear Charley…", 30 May 1881 (4.26 [B.195])
  - "Dear Charley…" Hartford, 31 May 1881 (4.27 [B.196])
  - Telegram to unidentified correspondent, Hartford, 17 June 1881 (4.28 [B.197])
  - "Dear Charley…" Branford, 20 June 1881 (4.29 [B.198])
  - "Dear Charley…" Sunday, 1881 (4.30 [B.199])
  - "Dear Charley…" Branford, 21 June 1881 (4.31 [B.200])